# TINASHE G. GWATIRINGA

Newlands 7700 Cape Town Cell: +27 71 581 9415
Email: <u>GWTTIN002@myuct.ac.za</u>
Website: <a href="https://tinashe-gwatiringa.github.io/">https://tinashe-gwatiringa.github.io/</a>

An enthusiastic Mechatronic Engineering graduate from the University of Cape Town. The team-based structure of my research project speaks volumes to my ability to work well in a team. Also a hands-on person with the ability to quickly grasp and apply new concepts and systems.

#### **EDUCATION**

### 2016-Present: University of Cape Town (UCT) - MSc Electrical Engineering

- Research topic: Sea State Estimation using the Wave Glider Platform.
- Supervisor: Professor E. Boje (UCT).

### 2012-2015: University of Cape Town (UCT) - BSc Mechatronic Engineering

• Graduated December 2015 with Honours.

### 2011-2012: University of Cape Town (UCT) - BSc Construction Management

• Completed first year and transferred to BSc. Mechatronics.

### 2009-2010: St John's College, Harare - International Baccalaureate (IB) Diploma

• 3 of 6 subjects taken at an advanced level including Mathematics, Physics and Chemistry.

### 2007-2008: St John's College, Harare - Cambridge IGCSE (O-Levels)

Obtained the highest results in a class of 120, with an A\* aggregate in 7 of 8 subjects.

### **KEY STRENGTHS & SKILLS**

- Leadership: Vice Chairman of the UCT Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineers (IEEE) student chapter where responsibilities include planning of student events and recruitment of new members.
- **Communication:** As a teaching assistant for various courses, developed skills in clear communication to both students and tutors, ensuring efficient course management.
- Time Management and Planning: Skills improved through having teaching responsibilities concurrently with a full postgraduate schedule.
- IT: Proficient Linux and Windows user; competent in C, C++, Python, Matlab, Latex, Microsoft Office, as well as simulation software LabVIEW and Simulink.
- Languages: Fluent in English and French.

### **ACHIEVEMENTS AND LEADERSHIP POSITIONS**

- 2017: Awarded the John Davidson Scholarship award.
- 2013-2014: Peer Mentor, providing support and advice for First Year Engineering students.
- 2012: Invited to be a member of the International Golden Key Honour Society.
- 2011-2012: Placed on Dean's Merit List (for students with GPA above 70%).
- 2010: Appointed Music Leader at St John's College.
- 2008: Academic Colours Award for best Cambridge IGCSE (O-level) results.

• 2007: One of six pupils selected to represent Zimbabwe at the International Junior Science Olympiad (IJSO) held in Taiwan.

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

#### Feb 2017 - Present: Teaching Assistant for Embedded Systems

- Responsible for a team of 12 tutors for a large undergraduate course split into two modules with two teaching assistants.
- Improved teamwork skills through co-management of the tutor group, by creating a spreadsheet tool for time logging, reporting and dynamic assignment of tutors for the different modules.

### Jul 2016 - Jan 2017: Tutor for Computer Integrated Manufacture and Robotics

- Improved my robotics knowledge working as a tutor.
- Duties included conducting robotics practicals mostly done in LabVIEW.

#### Jun 2016 - Dec 2016: Private Tutor for Club Electron

- An initiative that fosters a passion for science and creative thinking in young children.
- Gained valuable inter-personal skills whilst helping the children and other instructors engage with the content.

### Feb 2016 - Jun 2016: Teaching Assistant for Signals and Systems

• Gained administrative experience as a teaching assistant, duties for which included setting, conducting and marking tutorials, managing tutors and test marking.

### Jun 2014 - Jul 2014: Student Intern at Radar Remote Sensing Group (RRSG)

- Worked in a close team of 5, giving valuable teamwork experience.
- Developed organisation skills whilst working on a thermal design and enclosure project that required sensitive
  equipment to be used in adverse conditions.

### Nov 2013 - Jan 2014: British American Tobacco (BAT)

Worked as an Engineer in Training where exposure at an industrial level gave a deeper understanding of PLC
programming and maintenance, electrical diagnosis and troubleshooting as well as motor maintenance and
repairs.

### **TECHNICAL TRAINING & CONFERENCES**

- 2016: PRASA-RobMech Robotics Conference held in Stellenbosch.
- 2016: Optimal Estimation for Control Engineers Course.
- 2012: Cape Peninsula University of Technology (CPUT) Mechanical Engineering Practical Training workshop.

### SOCIAL OUTREACH & OTHER INTERESTS

- Regular tutoring volunteer for the Robogals Society, which encourages young girls to pursue a career in the engineering field by teaching them basic electronics.
- Engaged with the underprivileged children of Hupenyu Hutsva where I repaired their broken marimbas and gave the children some basic music lessons.
- A member of the Mechatronics Research Group social squash club.
- Enjoy playing tennis; member of the social tennis club at UCT.
- Played a leading role in the St John's Marimba Band, and continue to play socially.

## **REFEREES**

• Ms. Robyn A. Verrinder: Digital Electronics Lecturer

Electrical Engineering Department, University of Cape Town

Email: <a href="mailto:robyn.verrinder@uct.ac.za">robyn.verrinder@uct.ac.za</a>

• Professor Edward Boje: Head of Department

Electrical Engineering Department, University of Cape Town

Email: edward.boje@uct.ac.za